Battle for Saipan is a war, history, action film directed by Brandon Slagle.
On July 7, 1944, a U.S.
Army hospital on the remote island of Saipan is overrun by
Japanese forces during a relentless attack.
Outgunned and surrounded by the enemy, a lone medic puts it all on
the line to lead a band of wounded soldiers to safety.
Vic, played by Casper Van Dien.
General Jake Carroll, played by Jeff Fahey.
Major William Porter, played by Louis Mandylor.
Sofia, played by Jennifer Wenger.
Ava, played by Devanny Pinn.
Inessa, played by Natalya Nikolaeva.
Saipan () is the largest island and capital of the Northern Mariana Islands, an
unincorporated territory of the United States in the western Pacific Ocean.
According to 2020 estimates by the United States Census
Bureau, the population of Saipan was 43,385.
Its people have been United States citizens since the 1980s.
Saipan is one of the main homes of the Chamorro and the
Carolinian, the indigenous people of the Mariana Islands.
From the 17th century, the island experienced Spanish occupation and rule until the Spanish–American War of
1898, when Saipan was briefly occupied by the United States, before being formally sold to Germany.
About 15 years of German rule were followed by 30 years of Japanese rule, which was ended by the
Battle of Saipan, as the United States began to take control of the Philippine Sea.
Following World War II, Saipan became part of the Trust Territory of the Pacific Islands, and was
administered by the United States, along with the rest of the Northern Marianas.
In 1978, Saipan formally joined the United States as part of the
Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands.
Today, Saipan is home to about 90% of the
population of the Northern Mariana Islands.
It hosts many resorts, golf courses, beaches, nature
sites, and World War II historical sites.
The legislative and executive branches of Commonwealth government are located in the village of Capitol
Hill on the island while the judicial branch is headquartered in the village of Susupe.
Since the entire island is organized as a single municipality, most
publications designate Saipan as the Commonwealth's capital.
As of 2025, Saipan's mayor is Ramon Camacho and the governor
of the Northern Mariana Islands is David M.
Saipan was hit by Super Typhoon Yutu in 2018, which caused widespread damage.
In 2015, it was hit by another Super Typhoon, Soudelor, causing
extensive damage to houses and commercial property.